all right hello and welcome it's August
5th 2024 this is active inference guest
stream
85.1 deep learning active inference with
love with David blumen so thank you
David for the presentation and we'll
look forward to the
[Music]
discussion um yeah
how we can uh use active
inference to make intelligent agent and
uh some of the advantages and
disadvantages and some issues with
active inference and how I think we can
overcome them um and you'll see why
would love uh in a little bit but uh my
background is I'm a software engineer
and an AI researcher uh I've uh worked
for a really long time at the section of
uh scalable systems and machine learning
and I've been working on this project
for about three years now um and I'm
really excited to uh talk about it so uh
I think uh the Holy Grail of uh AI
research uh right now is how do we make
an AI agent that's both generally
intelligent and doesn't destroy Humanity
uh and uh
pretty much I think most people are
working on some facet of these two U and
uh I'm really excited about the
generally intelligent part and also not
destroying Humanity so um here's how I
think we can do it but first I want to
talk about just like get our definitions
so what's an agent and there's lots of
people arguing about definitions uh I'm
going to use a really simple one which
is an agent is something that uh G given
a set of past observations produces the
next action so basically given what
you're seeing now and what you've seen
and experienced in the past what should
you do next so a very uh simple
formulation of an agent as a
function and by generally
intelligent uh I don't have uh a
rigorous definition of general
intelligence I don't actually think
there is one but uh as an observer
observing this agent we should be able
to say hey it's it's acting smart in a
wide variety of environments that it
hasn't seen before um and what that
means is that it's able to figure out
the environment Dynamics it's able to
make mistakes and learn from them it uh
doesn't get stuck at the local Optima it
like knows when to explore but then when
it figures out regularities about the
environment it knows how to use them uh
it does this efficiently it's not just
like trying the same uh dumb thing over
and over again uh it makes plans it can
uh communicate and interact with other
uh complex intelligent entities in the
environment so it's a bunch of different
behaviors and uh uh I don't think
there's a really clear way to quantify
or like talk about that exactly what
they look like because different spaces
and different environments uh are going
to have a different idea of what an
intelligent agent is doing there uh so
uh for now just like think of it as this
grab bag of
capabilities so where does active
inference come in well active inference
uh is a way of thinking about an agent
interacting with its environment as uh
essentially a u it's a formulation where
any agent can be seen as if it was uh
acting in a self- evidencing way and
what that means is that uh you can treat
any object uh that maintains homeostasis
over time as if the inside of that
object was minimizing free energy uh
meaning that it had some some you can
think of it as having some generative
model of its environment or rather from
an agents perspective its boundary and
it is uh trying to update its prior
beliefs or is posterior beliefs over the
boundary in order to minimize surprise
and so the way it does that is when it
uh receives evidence from the
environment uh it uh adjusts its set of
beliefs to Concord with what it thinks
it's GNA what the environment is and
what it's doing and where it is in that
environment but it's also actively
navigating the environment in order to
both U Get gather more knowledge and
improve its uh set of beliefs as well as
to move into parts of the environment
that it thinks it's going to be
occupying uh and so this is a really
beautiful way to capture what any agent
is doing at any scale so this
formulation uh allows us to think about
uh a biological cell or a robot or a
person or an organization a corporation
a country uh anything that we want to
draw a boundary around we can basically
say hey this thing is kind of acting as
if it was doing basian inference over
its input data and had PR beliefs over
uh a set of states that it's going to be
occupying and it's trying to uh act in
accordance with
that so the problem with that
formulation so the nice thing about that
formulation is it's very general it's
very beautiful uh it uh is able to
generalize uh what we see at different
scales one thing that it doesn't let us
do is actually tell us how do we
build such an agent and there are two
reasons that I think uh that this theory
is not uh is not useful for actually
building an agent um one is that uh it
uh treats every agent as trying to
approximate basian inference uh so as
the agent observes evidence it's trying
to uh infer what that means for its
generative model and trying to update
its posterior the problem with basian
inference is that it is computationally
intractable and uh uh the uh active
inference recognizes this and it
basically says the agent is trying to
approximately do basian inference by
sticking a variational inference bound
on it but in reality what approximately
means uh is different in every situation
so U uh all agents that we see all
systems that we see they're doing some
kind of computation and that computation
can be viewed as approximate basic
inference but in reality it's a set of
puristic and hacks that have been
discovered by evolution by natural
selection by software Engineers whatever
it is that uh can be thought of as
approximately doing this um but really
they're running some algorithm it's just
some set of theistic and active
inference doesn't really tell us how to
discover that it just says says Hey
anything it's doing can be viewed as
approximately doing this intractable
problem the other problem uh uh around
trying to productionize active inference
is that it says well the agent is going
to be occupying uh a set of states that
its prior beliefs said it's going to be
occupying so you know why does uh an
animal eat well because Evolution has uh
filtered uh animals down to only the
animals that believe that they're going
to be fed and so then the animal is
going to Via self- evidencing Way go
seek out food and again this is a really
beautiful way to capture uh uh both uh
the action and inference in one uh
formulation but it doesn't tell you what
are the priors Over States for a given
environment so if you want to build a a
robot or an agent that has to interact
with some environment what what are its
prior beliefs what states should it be
occupying does it believe that it's
going to get energy or does it believe
it's going to go repair uh you know the
car that you wanted to repair how does
it balance between those two um uh we
don't know and active inference doesn't
really tell us it just says some process
uh will give you a set of priors and uh
so with active inference typically the
approach is well as a software engineer
uh you build a uh generative model you
basically code up what you think the
environment requires and the agent in
the environment requires and you give it
some priors like you will be fed and you
will repair this car and here's uh some
parameters about how the environment
works that are uh simple enough that you
can then do a variational inference over
it and get something done and then you U
have a more generic free energy minimiz
minimizing algorithm that then given
that generative model actually controls
the robot the approach I want I'm taking
is well instead of uh someone trying to
design this General model can we learn
it and uh I think that's really the only
way forward because any environment that
we care about is going to be so complex
that I just don't believe humans are
going to be able to uh specify
generative model for it that's at all
interesting so uh why do I think we can
learn it well uh one Evolution has and
uh what does learning it mean uh
learning means uh that we want to use
some Learning System and uh neural Nets
are a really good one and we want to
figure out what are the sets we
basically want to have some approximate
active inference agents some approximate
generative model that uh is able to do
all the things we want which is that
grab bag of generally intelligent
behaviors and the reason we can do that
is that neural networks are Universal
function approximators so rather than
building an algorithm we took a neural
network we FedEd uh you know pairs of
text and images and out comes dolly that
given text is just able to generate uh
images uh also generator all the slides
for this presentation
um so uh the way to think about neural
networks is rather than programming an
algorithm you figure out the training
data and a loss function and then you
take a Big Blob of learning uh uh
learnable parameters and you keep
nudging that blob until it uh does what
you want it to do and this technique is
really powerful you know uh we're uh
language models that uh everyone is
using now uh uh were also trained this
way you uh took a data set that was a
set of prompts and a set and then a
completion basically the next word uh
and uh uh you trained a neural network
to predict the next word and you got
chat GPT so uh this technique uh is
extremely powerful it is very slow it
requires a lot of data and a lot of
training examples but over time uh
you're able to learn a really
complicated uh function
approximator so uh the the question then
is okay well if we want to train a
function approximator for a generally
intelligent agent what's the training
data that we need to use and uh uh
basically I think if we discover the
training data and we uh throw large
neural network at it with a lot of
compute we should be able to in the same
way that we got chpt or Dolly get a
model that's like a foundational General
intelligent agent model so to do that we
need an
environment and uh what an environment
so the reason we need an environment is
that we're trying to train an agent not
uh say a language model so for language
model you give it a prefix uh it gives
you uh the completion and you can train
it on say all of the internet text what
we're trying to do is we're trying to
learn a function that given a set of
fast observations know what action to do
next and uh that's a more complicated
problem because sometimes the action it
takes should be uh done because it's
trying to accomplish something sometimes
it's because it's trying to learn
something um sometimes it's trying to
explore uh and so what we need is a
world for the agent to interact with
that it can and then learn its behaviors
from and so the properties we need for
that environment is one we want it to
provide continuous learning
opportunities so there should always be
something that the agent some new thing
for the model to learn and uh then when
it learns it when it does something
intelligent uh one of these behaviors
that we uh associate with intelligence
we want we need a feedback signal so we
need the environment to essentially
reward it and it needs to be not uh an
environment that cannot be mastered
because um if it can ever be mastered
then there's nothing new to learn and
the model stops
learning so the way to set that up is uh
or one way to set that up is uh via
multi-agent so if you have an
environment uh even if it's a relatively
simple one like say a go game where the
rules of the game are really simple uh
just by having other agents in that
environment uh give it a really
important property as the agent gets
smarter so do the competitors and so uh
the environment essentially adapts to
your capabilities uh so this is a way
where uh you can automatically get an
environment that always gets uh
something uh new for you to do because
as soon as you learn some exploit or
some way of uh being better than your
competition the competition changes and
now you have to learn something new
and so I think uh so my Approach is
leveraging uh this uh characteristic and
essentially training AIS in a
multi-agent competitive environment
there is a problem though which is if
the environment is entirely
competitive uh you very quickly end up
at this U kill or beill dynamic so you
can imagine uh an agent learns some
Behavior policy and then the other agent
learns some counter strategy and then
they kind of explore the area around
those strategies and figure out the best
way to be competitive and now they're
stuck because if any agent ever tries to
do anything that is not that it gets
exploited by its adversary so um this
setup makes it really hard to uh avoid
local Maxima you kind of find something
that works and you're stuck there and
that's not quite true if you have many
agents you might get some unstable
symmetry breaking and uh uh things get
smoothed out a little bit but um I think
the solution to that is actually
cooperation and what's cool about
cooperation is U there are many ways to
cooperate the space of effective
behaviors when it comes to cooperation
uh just explodes and so you end up with
a u much uh denser more higher
dimensional Behavior space where it's
harder to ever get stuck at some uh Nash
equilibrium of uh
behaviors and this also gives rise to
complex group dynamics uh like Coalition
building cooperation uh cooperating to
compete figuring out who you're going to
cooperate with and who you're going to
compete with uh building trust uh it's
just like the set of behaviors that are
available in Cooperative environments
explodes and the problem with
cooperation is it's really hard to learn
if all the agents are selfish it's not
possible you can have things like
reciprocal altruism or even just
non-aggression you can learn that you
know always picking a fight is not great
because if even if you win the fight now
you're weaker and someone else can take
advantage of you but uh in general uh uh
learning cooperation when everyone is
non-cooperative is also full of these um
ntion equilibria of local Optima and
nature solves this using kinship so when
an animal is born into a world it is not
surrounded by uh other selfish organisms
it's surrounded by a lot of kin uh so uh
for cellular organisms it's surrounded
by more or less identical genetic clones
of it uh for Animals uh it's surrounded
by organisms that have half of its genes
and uh this uh kinship uh via genetic
Evolution gives rise to organisms that
are not selfish because uh from a gen's
perspective uh having a copy of you in
one organism or in another organism
doesn't matter and so what that does is
it gives rise to organisms that
basically care about the success of
other organisms almost as much as they
care about the success of their own
organism and there's a whole Spectrum in
nature from hive insects like ants where
from a soldier's ants perspective the
only way for those genes to make it into
the next generation is for the queen to
reproduce and so you end up with ants
that care a lot more about the hive and
the queen than they care about their own
safety and well-being and uh you get a
whole Spectrum from fully altruistic
Hive uh insects to you know a few
perfectly selfish sociopaths but uh most
animals fall somewhere in the middle and
being in the Middle where you're
partially selfish and partially uh uh
altruistic gives rise to all of these
social behaviors that we associate with
uh being an intelligent uh being so uh
animals coordinate they uh negotiate
they build trust they love each other
they show kindness they show jealousy
they have social emotions like shame
they uh learn how to exchange exchange
uh knowledge with each other via gossip
and reputation building they do division
of labor and all of these things happen
again at every layer of complexity
animals do it uh biological cells do it
uh organizations do it uh these set sets
of behaviors are present in uh pretty
much all entities that we think are
intelligent and so my proposal back to
this uh AGI recipe is that uh if we can
have the right training data and enough
compute uh we can train a large model on
an environment that uh essentially
balances U cooperation and competition
and so I've been trying to build and
design uh these environment this
environment and the training
infrastructure for it and that's been uh
essentially uh my research Direction so
this is uh the current version of the
environment uh and I'll just uh talk
through some of the components so you
can see there's uh a few agents here and
they're uh they're parameterized by our
neural network so all of this was
trained from scratch using reinforcement
learning uh there is this heart alter in
the middle and uh the only source of
reward that these agents have is they um
can walk up to the heart alter and they
can use it which requires energy and if
they do that they get a reward and what
that means is that these agents have to
get more energy out of their environment
than they're using for interacting and
competing with each other uh and if they
can extract more energy than they need
and they can essentially waste it by
putting it into this heart alter then
they get a reward so this is the
competitive Dynamic that's set up so
everything uh doing everything in this
environment requires energy to get
energy you collect these resources so
you walk up to a green or yellow Crystal
and you collect a resource um you then
have to walk up to these converter
stations that look like little batteries
and then you put the right set of
resources in there and you get energy
out you can also attack each other and
if you get uh shot you turn into this
egg where you're stationary for a while
you lose some time and people can steal
whatever resources you're carrying but
you can also turn on a shield which also
costs energy uh but then it deflects the
attacks so these a have to from scratch
learn how do you navigate the space
where are the resources uh how do you
manage your energy budget who do you
fight with who do you uh not fight with
when do you need to keep your shield on
so a lot of like relatively intelligent
behaviors uh that are learned from
scratch and all of this is done via this
competitive uh Dynamic and then on top
of that is a uh whole system for kinship
where uh every agent shares its reward
with some other agents based on some uh
reward sharing uh system and so what
that means is um whenever say this red
agent gets a a reward uh the green agent
might get 10% of that reward and so this
environment allows you to train uh
agents in very different environment so
um I'm going to pause this and switch
over to uh
this other tab so
um yeah here so here you know you can
train in larger maps you can uh uh set
up different uh game rules and different
game
scenarios um and you can also uh set up
different kinship environments where you
can train fully selfish agents you can
train fully uh Cooperative agents you
can uh train complex nonsymmetric
uh social
dynamics and once you train an agent you
can actually start treating it like an
intelligence and you can do Behavioral
Studies on it so here we take a trained
agent that was trained in this
environment and we just like put it in
an empty room and we're like well what
what is this agent doing and you can see
it's like it's exploring its environment
it's not getting close to any walls
because it knows that there's not a lot
to be seen uh and it doesn't want to
waste its movement um you can put it in
an environment
of uh where uh you know you give it some
energy and you give it U and you put it
in a world where there's nothing except
this heart alter and you'll see that it
like searches the world until it finds
the heart alter and then it puts energy
in there um and so uh you can start
doing uh you can essentially study it
and do experiments on it it's like what
will it do under this
circumstances um and you can start
approaching some of this as an observer
observing an an intelligent entity um
this is all early days so this is just a
few uh evals and experiments that I've
been setting up but this environment
allows you to do all of these
things
um and I think what's cool about this uh
whole approach um and I'll switch back
to this slide is that uh the idea is
that uh you you end up with an
environment that is unlearnable because
anytime some agent gets some competitive
Advantage it uh the environment around
it changes since all the other agents
now Arbitrage away that Advantage it's
also uh highly uh highly dense in
Behavior space because there's so many
different ways to uh cooperate and
compete with each other that uh there's
always some new trick that you can
discover
and so as this neural network learns to
achieve Fitness to this environment uh
and the environment is always changing
it's also learning how to learn it's
learning this set of adaptive behaviors
of exploring uh forming theories testing
things out uh because that's the
behavior that gives it an advantage when
the environment is always changing and
so uh the hope is to end up with a uh
with an agent that you can drop into a
new environment that it hasn't seen
before and the thing it'll do is first
figure out the Dynamics of the
environment to start exploring it figure
out how to uh how different things work
and then what it needs to do and then
start doing it um the other cool thing
about this setup is because these agents
are trained in a Cooperative setting
they have to cooperate with they have to
learn how to cooperate with other agents
and that means they have to learn how to
communicate so there's a uh signaling
and a language component uh so if you
are surrounded by kin and you have to
compete with another group you have to
learn what information is necessary to
communicate to your allies in order to
effectively organized so these agents
are developing a language that we can
then um be able to reverse engineer
because we have a fully instrumented
world uh and we can do experiments on
them so we can basically figure out what
is it is that they're saying and we can
then talk to them and they're uh
learning a policy that's conditioned on
this kinship score uh so they know how
to cooperate with close skin which means
they are capable of Cooper they're
learning to be capable of cooperation
they're essentially learning to care for
other agents and so the hope of This
research uh program is to build a model
organism of um an active inference agent
essentially an agent that is performing
active inference in a complex
environment that you can talk to and
that cares uh about other agents in that
environment um and if that works we
should be able to uh take these same
ideas and um take it out of this simple
2D grid World environment and
essentially do the same thing but in
complex 3D World physics environments uh
and get something that is smart that
cares about other entities and that we
can talk to um so that's basically what
I'm trying to do I'm calling this
project meta learning um meta is the
poly word for love and kindness uh
because I think that um Love is uh love
and uh what I think I'm building here
are agents that are capable of love in
the same way that genetic Evolution um
the selfishness of a gene being
expressed in uh a multitude of other
organisms gave rise to organisms that
love and care for each other especially
their K I think that similar Dynamic uh
is what's necessary to uh create um a an
environment that's complex enough to
learn uh generalized intelligent
behavior and also is going to create
agents that U are alignable that
basically care for other agents that we
can get along with so um I I'll stop uh
talking here and uh uh take questions uh
and uh yeah happy to dive into anything
uh that I talked about or if you have
questions about active inference or how
or free energy or deep learning uh
basically anything that this made you
think about I'm so happy to take
questions awesome all
right anyone in live chat please feel
free to
ask a question just meanwhile maybe just
H how did you come to be applying it the
neural network approaches in this
project just what what L you want to
explore this project and then how do you
see active inference playing a
role yeah uh I mean uh it's funny
because um I uh I've moved in and out of
uh machine learning my entire career uh
uh and uh the experience I've had was I
would go into AI I would spend a bunch
of time working on it and then I'd be
like okay the field is not ready like we
don't know what we're doing and I took a
long pause uh and worked at a startup
for 10 years and um after leaving that
startup I came across uh Carl friston's
free energy work and um had been out of
AI for uh almost a
decade um missed the last two
revolutions uh and reading it uh it just
kind of clicked for me I was like okay
like I can see how because this
describes intelligence at every scale
and just very naturally falls out of
what it means for uh objects to maintain
homeostasis in an entropic environment
and I can see what the math uh looks
like the math looks like uh
essentially uh the math from
reinforcement learning it's uh trying to
um do basing an inference on your uh
evidence to compute a posterior uh and
navigate an environment in order to
balance exploration exploitation um and
that's kind of what the reinforcement
learning community came up with bottoms
up uh just like trying to be like how
hey how do we train uh an entity that
learns in its environment and when I
when I saw just how close those two
approaches were to each other it really
made me feel like okay there's no secret
sauce in it's like there's not something
that we're missing that's key to
intelligence that we just like haven't
been able to capture really it is like
uh this uh kind of exploration
exploitation inference
combination uh and uh now it's just like
how do we build it and the more I uh
started thinking about this the more I
was like well active inference doesn't
tell you how to build it it tells you
that uh a bunch of these things have to
be either filtered for we discovered uh
and green forcement learning kind of
starts out with the idea of like well we
don't know what we're doing how do we
build it how we discover it and so then
I started exploring the whole spectrum
between the two uh you know do you start
out with a world model that you learn
but then you have a a set of algorithms
that use that world model in some
predictable way or do you learn the
entire thing as a behavioral policy end
to endend uh uh and I see these as
essentially pragmatic de pragmatic
engineering decisions uh but uh just
like having the confidence that this
approach is essentially what all
intelligent entities are doing really
pulled me back into this field U and
once I realize that uh uh what an agent
is really doing is not some idealized
version of uh infer active inference
because the idealized version is
computationally intractable
that really led me to be like okay it's
not doing this perfect thing it's doing
this approximate thing so if everything
is doing an approximate thing and we
have the technology to learn an
approximator uh we we should just be
able to do that uh just like have a
thing that learns the set of hacks and
heris that any actual agent is going to
have to uh discover uh and uh we have
the existence proof of being able to do
this in other problem spaces like
language awesome that's super
informative I'll just let you have a sip
of water and kind of reach a few of the
key pieces because I think these are
really key so because free energy
principle and active inference describe
like any SL every
scale it has come across some of these
same issues that reinforcement learning
has come across on the low road that's
why active inference is like between the
high road and the low road because of
how the architectures are it's not just
a specific architecture it's almost like
as you're pointing out because of the
fact it's already an approximation
because even the analytical part is an
approximation the analytical part is
variational inference so already talking
about an approximation to a perfect map
so at that point it really is pragmatic
like you described whether you approach
this in like a well structured way and
there are often an active inference
people like talk about like structure
learning
and adding and shrinking parameters and
hooking up different things doing
combinatorics with Bas graphs and that
that may be super promising for certain
pieces and like keeping it well typed
and well defined and then the other
approach which is resonating with with
how you're saying big problems and other
domains have been solved is like
actually an interestingly open-ended
approach which is the like you said
reinforcement uh Universal function
approximator so it's a complimentary
approach to try to use a statistical
approximator of the variational
inference so my first question is H how
about that
reward function can you specify it
different ways or have you specified it
different ways for example the reward
could be when two people interact and
don't have a conflict or different
things um because just from a sort of uh
predictability perspective it's like
it's it's actually a power preference
centralization so you've taken a really
flat uniform informative approach to any
distribution except for one and loaded
all the hopes and dreams on one so what
do you think that does with the
architecture yeah great question um I W
to uh uh respond to that first I want to
respond to something you just said a
little bit earlier uh in terms of uh
like structure uh models U as the
generative model for active inference uh
I think what's cool about the free
energy principle is that it just like
lets you rephrase anything that a system
is doing as if it was it had some
generative model and it's uh minimizing
free energy on it so uh any any Behavior
can be rephrased as a uh as free energy
minimization over some set of uh some
generative model over some set of
beliefs uh and so it's like a really
nice way to just go between two uh two
ways of formulating uh uh problem and uh
I think the people that try to take the
more principled less design a generative
model for it uh the challenges they run
into is well whatever model they're
designing whatever graph they're
designing um has for in order to be
computationally tractable with
variational uh uh minimization uh is
some sparse graph of random variables uh
with some sparsity constraints and then
they're like well what what are the what
does this graph look like and uh either
they're making it up or they're trying
to learn it uh but uh if if you're
trying to learn it you're kind of back
to this thing of like well we don't know
what the generative model is let's try
to learn it uh but uh so I I I I see uh
these approaches as kind of being
equivalent is just like how much prior
structure do you uh Force onto the
system and then when you actually use so
uh when you do uh say variational Bays
what you have what you're saying is look
I have this structure and I'm not saying
this structure represents reality but I
think this can represent reality uh to
some eror and then I have this inference
mechanism uh that I'm applying to this
structure and together we are
representing reality uh some
approximation of reality uh with some
air term and um what's cool about uh
being able to do uh doing an end to
endend thing where you're just like ah
throw your hands up and be like I want
to learn the whole thing is that uh the
set of uh the set of inference
algorithms that you get to explore are
also more powerful so for example you
can imagine uh parts of the model where
it's like really important to get uh
some detail right whereas other parts of
the model it's like it's not that
important you know what this random
variable says it's like it doesn't have
a lot of effect on the downstream task
so when you're doing free energy
minimization uh you uh you don't get to
choose which part uh of your model is
important how much compute to spend on
different parts of it uh whereas when
you're learning an algorithm end to
endend part of the thing you're learning
is when to do how much inference and how
much your inference matters so I think
this is another uh kind of way in which
uh the the more principled approaches uh
pull in an assumption that maybe is a
reasonable assumption maybe is not but
is definitely limiting uh yeah if I if I
can just rate I think that's very
farsighted of a of a way to understand
this because let's just say we're using
an RX and fur. JL strongly typed Julia
language model the decisions about when
and how to optimize the message passing
timing and when would itself maybe it's
irrelevant to the the question or maybe
you don't need the most efficient but if
you need open-endedness on how the graph
is orchestrated then it just shows that
in realistic even small settings the
structured method is embedded within an
unstructured method now that's either a
manual curation like which might happen
for small scale but if you're talking
large scale generative model then even
that outer Orchestra of level is
essentially statistical so that's that's
a really important thing to remember and
all these other like kind of pragmatic
considerations about the data
infrastructure and all these types of
things which are like again they're not
in the textbook but to get above even a
small size run they start coming into
play and now I want to talk about the
reward question that you asked and I
think that's a really great question uh
this is actually uh so uh right now and
this is early days for this project but
right now the reward is this heart alter
and uh uh plus kinship uh and uh the
thing that I wanted to do with reward is
we need some reinforcement signal from
the environment to essentially uh uh
reinforce the policy so the policy needs
to learn from something it needs some
learning signal and what I wanted to do
was uh make a system where you don't
have to keep messing with the system you
just get to scale things up and so you
make it environment and then you just
scale up the size of the models in the
environment and as you do that the
environment gets more and more complex
in an open-ended way because the
environment is really the minds of the
other learning agents not the physical
game and so uh the thing I wanted out of
the reward was uh something that binds
the agents to each other and to the
environment and so it had to be some
kind of uh competitive Dynamic uh
essentially there has to be something
that when one agent is doing better than
another agent uh essentially there's
some Zero Sum uh uh finite reward to go
around so that uh there's pressure on
the agents to uh be smart smarter and by
smarter be meaning figure out a way to
behave that gives it an advantage over
some
counterfactual uh other agent uh so
that's the idea behind the this uh uh
reward the other thing I wanted from the
reward is I wanted it to be really
sparse so that you're not constantly U
tinkering around it's like Oh I wanna uh
you know I want these agents to do
something more interesting I want them
to cooperate more let me add a reward
for cooperation or like for this
interaction I basically I don't want to
be in the uh in the game of environment
design and reward tinkering I want
something that's just and I think it's
this is a really beautiful reward it's
essentially free energy it's uh you know
from an agent's perspective their job is
to extract energy from the environment
and then use it to compete with each
other and then if you ever find yourself
with excess of energy that's your reward
and this is uh you get this in evolution
where it's like hey if you can uh get
enough energy to
reproduce uh if you can muster enough
energy to make a copy of yourself that
is the reward for the genes that's how
the Gene gets into the Next Generation
so you can think of this as a
reproduction reward you can think of
this uh partially what I'm doing is kind
of re uh trying to pull the ideas from
uh biological natural selection into
reinforcement learning and so this is um
from a genetic perspective when you make
a copy of yourself it means you got
enough energy out of the environment you
made a copy of yourself and so the genes
get reinforced those are the genes that
then persist similarly here when you got
more energy than the competition and you
went and put that into the heart alar U
uh it means that the policy is
reinforced and so those are the policies
that you're going to see originally I
didn't even have the heart alter I just
had an action that an agent could take
that burns energy and gives it reward so
it was essentially
self-rewarding and uh I did the hard
alter just because it was like easier to
visualize as a human watching it it's
like oh yeah they walk over there they
do thing uh you can think of it as like
laying an egg uh essentially and so the
other aspect of the reward is the the
kinship so when you get a reward uh
other agents are getting some of that
reward uh as well so your source of
reward is not just walking up to the
heart alar it's also helping other
agents do it uh and learning who those
agents are and under what circumstances
you should help one agent and not the
other and uh at what point should a
resource go to some other agent uh and
not to you uh so the reward function is
actually really complex from an agent's
uh perspective because uh it is this U
social uh social reward rather than just
a selfish one and then one more thing
I'll add which is like really inspired
by active inference that I haven't yet
implemented but um is very close on my
road map is um one problem with a sparse
reward is it's really hard for agents to
learn because a lot of times you're
doing stuff and you're not getting any
feedback uh and then sometimes you get a
reward but it's not even something you
did it's something some other agent did
that's your kid uh and so this is a
really hard learning problem uh in
reinforcement learning and one thing
that active inference gave us is this
idea of surprise minimization as an
auxiliary reward so um a reward that I
plan to add to an agent is that there's
going to be some small amount of reward
that you get just from being able to
predict your observation at the next
time step and what that allows you to do
is and it's going to be a really small
reward because you don't want to
overwhelm the competitive landscape uh
you don't want the agent to just be uh
you know all I care about is predicting
you know hiding in a hole and predicting
my environment you wanted to engage with
the rest of the world
uh but what this gives you is a very
dense learning signal essentially at
every time step even if you're not
getting some reward from the environment
you're able to learn some environment
Dynamics because there's this uh reward
signal about just like um uh figuring
out how the world is working and I I
actually think that uh at the limit uh
you don't need this because at the limit
being able to uh uh learning a policy
that is able to get this competitive
reward requires that you uh learn a
policy that's also a good World model
that is always predicting what's going
to happen uh with more weight on the
things that actually matter so it's like
a pragmatic World model instead of just
like you know I want to predict all of
my observations uh World model which is
why you can't really give it uh give the
predictive reward too much of a weight
because not all the things that you're
observing matter uh there's an Infinity
of things you can predict about your
environment and you don't want the agent
to be trying to predict them all you
want it to be trying to predict the
things that matter but I do think that
it'll make agents that uh learn faster
uh at least initially when they don't
know how the environment is behaving
yeah again a huge Point even epistemic
value you at some level have to do
statistics to figure out the right
balancing between epistemic and
pragmatic all right I there's a bunch of
questions in the chat so I'm just going
to give you these questions in the order
so feel free just to give response as
you see it
okay board Guy 112 wrote in systems that
lack the architectural capabilities for
temporal or counterfactual depth how
does the process of minimizing free
energy relate to their form of epistemic
foraging
Behavior how is collective epistemic
foraging different with increasing like
agent level sophistic ation in terms of
not being able to plan just like
one-step planners versus like being able
to do more
planning yeah I think this is an
interesting question uh and I think
maybe I I missed uh the first part of it
but I can definitely respond to the
second part I don't know if there is
much of a difference um an agent is
something that takes its past
observations and then produces the next
action and I don't think there's a lot
of difference between an agent that is
planning versus an agent that is not
planning the question is how
sophisticated is the action going to be
so uh and you can think about this you
know you can have let's say you have a
thermostat right uh people don't even
want to call a thermostat an agent but
you have something that's trying to
control you know maintain temperature in
the room and you can have a planning
thermostat that says okay actually you
know uh I'm going to make a plan if I
increase uh the heat by this many then
here's my differential equ you know
here's my model of how that's going to
change the condition so I'm going to
instead or you can have a thermostat
that just like learned a really good uh
function that has uh that essentially it
unrolled the planning it's just like you
know what in this case I'm just going to
increase the temperature by this much
because that effectively is going to uh
turn into the right uh homeostasis
maintenance so um you the way I like to
think about it is you have a system and
it has some compute available to it and
it has um past observations and it's
going to produce the next action and
it's going to use that compute in some
way to figure out what uh that action is
and planning is a way that we can kind
of characterize what is it doing with
that with that compute does it have some
World model that we can understand and
it's doing some future rollouts on it or
uh we don't know what it's doing we can
treat it as if it was planning uh but
really it's just like is it able to
leverage the computer how much compute
does it have and is it able to leverage
that compute into uh achieving its goals
better or worse uh so I kind of think of
an agent that um is uh uh making
decisions just for the next time
interval uh as not that different than
an agent where you can explicitly say oh
it has a world model and it's doing
planning on it um it's just it's doing
some computation and it results in some
competence in achieving its goals
yeah great point it projects on to the
next action however you see it and
however it's done okay Courtney
wrote really cool work reminds me of
things like The Sims without humans
messing up their lives might the agents
eventually have some kind of
introspection in their model in a more
advanced simulation
get more and more uh uh uh like a bigger
and bigger part as we train bigger and
bigger networks so an agent that's
trying to do something uh needs to uh
essentially have some
trajectory uh right if an agent is
trying to get food it needs to keep uh
uh it's going to do a step towards the
food and then it's gonna have to do the
next step towards the food so it already
has some kind of uh internals that uh uh
give it consistent behaviors it has some
set of beliefs around U or can be
modeled as having some set of beliefs
around what its state is what its goal
state is in order to pursue that goal uh
it has to have theory of Mind of other
agents right the environment it works in
uh like whether or not it's going to get
its food depends on what all the other
agents around it are going to do like is
it going to get shot or not when it's
trying to go over there does it need to
turn on its Shield does it need to turn
off its Shield um so uh a lot of the
things that the agent is modeling are uh
the states of other agents and the
states of other agents depend on its
state you know maybe if it has a shield
on it's going to get shot but if it has
a shield off it's not going to get shot
so it has to um be uh in order to
predict what's going to happen to it it
has to know what other agents are going
to do which is a function of what it's
doing
so I think that's um that's key to uh
just like the whole thing uh working at
all so I think introspection is there
the the real question is how do we uh
how do we as external observers start
characterizing it having introspective
abilities uh and uh what experiments can
we perform to start uh quantifying you
know how much introspection does it have
uh and I think that's really a challenge
is not does it
what is it doing but how do we figure
out what it's doing how do we uh
distinguish an agent that has
introspection from one that doesn't or
has more introspection or not and that's
like a whole research agenda that I
think is like really interesting and I
would love help with awesome all right
John clippinger wrote can you have
Cooperative learning and reward rather
than zero Su allaha Martin Novak shoply
value
uh I mean yeah I think Cooperative
learning is what's happening here
because no agents reward is uh a zero
sum
reward I mean there is a zero sum reward
in over the whole system because there's
finiteness of resources and I think you
can't get away from that uh all all of
existence all of reality is essentially
allocating finite energy to infinite
potential compute so there is a zero
sumus nature to everything what's cool
about this Cooperative learning Dynamic
is that from every agent's perspective
it's not an individual agent it is some
uh smeared agent over other agents what
it cares about what it's trying to
maximize is uh some linear combination
of other agents uh uh including itself
so all of the learning is essentially
Cooperative learning uh from an agent's
perspective uh a close skin doing
something that gets it a reward is the
same as it doing it uh so we're kind of
blurring the line between you know is
this other agent just uh your left hand
versus your right hand or is this your
uh child brother parent or is this a
complete stranger uh and uh I think the
learning gets smeared across all of
those uh regimes yeah uh there's so many
more things I'll just make a short
comment and ask one or two more
questions um I I see it as as you're
you're using modern methods to bring in
a kind of mixed or multi-game Theory
because there might be some Nash Theory
or or clean analytical solution to like
some single dimensional game like a just
a this kind of game or just that kind of
game but when there's like tool use
opportunity cost co-
visibility it's it's not as simple as
just like as like a just buying and
selling on one
uncertainty so it and then also when you
consider the niche and Niche
modification through phermones as well
as through the collective defense in
like you social insects and naked mol
rats and all that kind of convergent
ecologies leading to evolutionary
transitions in the multiscale system and
then the further like canalization of
that for example the nestmate workers
who don't develop ovaries at all so at
that point calculating these partial
reproductive scores is is
nonfunctional okay I'm just going to
read read a few of the comments and then
um but first just what uh what are your
last or I mean sorry what are your next
uh moves and then I'll just redo these
the rest of the comments and you can
respond to anything but just where where
does this go SL where do you where do
you hope people can participate in
everything yeah oh great thanks for that
question um and I'll just throw out like
I don't have a hard end time so I'm to
go for as long as you're down um yeah uh
so uh my general plan is I'm approaching
this as an engineering problem it's an
open source project and what I want to
do is uh iterate on the environment
iterate on the training infrastructure
and iterate on the agent architecture uh
and iterate on the
evaluations uh and uh I'm kind of uh
approaching this like very improvisation
Al I'm just like okay what's the what's
the current bottleneck where do I think
I can uh get uh progress um and I would
love collaborators so part of where this
Pro like part of how I think this
project is going to work is based on who
I can get to help along with it but the
surface area of the project is huge it's
uh every every aspect of it is a bunch
of uh open-ended research directions
with uh like and what's really exciting
is like it's full of lwh hang fruit it's
like for every one of these directions I
have a bunch of ideas that are all
relatively easy that I'm pretty
confident are going to lead to really
cool results uh uh so there's a bunch of
stuff with environment design that is
really fun so uh uh the environment you
saw is really comp really simple it's
just like a few little game objects U I
have uh a whole uh library of uh new
game objects that I want to add that
will really change uh the dynamic so the
new version of the environment that I've
been building is entirely editable so
the agents can uh build and destroy all
objects while preserving uh total energy
in the environment
uh I have objects around like long range
communication uh I mean there's just
like so so many uh little game objects
that you can add that really alter the
nature of the envir environment uh
there's also because everything that you
do costs energy uh you can give so right
now when you train every uh training
episode the energy costs for all the
actions are sampled from some
distribution so sometimes movement is
really expensive and you have to learn
how to live in that world sometimes uh
attack is cheaper than defense sometimes
it's more expensive but one thing that
uh I'm really excited is to U actually
give different energy profiles
essentially different Bond IES to
different agents so that the environment
then becomes heterogeneous where
different agents have different
capabilities uh and the system has
support for that um I'm really excited
to add sexual selection where uh instead
of just uh agents uh having their
kinship determined uh at the beginning
of an episode uh they can actively
choose to become closer reward share uh
and I think that's going to un block a
lot of really complex uh Dynamics where
now you have to uh uh essentially
convince another agent that hey they
want a reward share with you and not
some other agent which gives rise to
signaling and counter signaling and uh
lying and I think was also like really
instrumental to Runaway intelligence and
human and primate uh Evolution so
there's uh that that is to say there's a
lot uh to do on the environment side uh
with like lots of really lohany fruit
there right now I'm uh working on
environment performance I'm rewriting
the environment in uh using a much more
performant architecture So currently I'm
training my models at around uh 40,000
steps per second uh which is pretty huge
uh on a single machine for reinforcement
learning for uh for people that are not
really involved the new environment uh
I'm hoping to get more uh like a million
uh steps per second so it's just gonna
mean that we can train bigger models
faster and really improve the iteration
speed for a lot of these experiments um
I have uh so um that's on the
environment side there's training
infrastructure there's a a few really
cool algorithms that I want to uh
Implement for distributed training so we
can train over uh many machines uh again
just trying to ramp up the training uh
uh evaluations is another thing that I'm
trying to develop is like how do we once
we have an agent how can we tell you
know is it smarter than the last agent
we built is it smarter than an agent
that has more or less a World Experience
how do we quantify that so there's a
bunch of stuff around evaluations and
cognitive tests and behavioral tests for
these agents that I uh uh I'm working on
uh and I'm just kind of uh picking out
from this giant collection of low
hanging fruit and going after that um um
in not a very principled way that's epic
that that sounds so cool okay tree harer
wrote are there any scalable Solutions
like with model-based RL for inferring
actions using deep active inference
instead of evaluating many policies
which might be computationally
intractable it's related to what we
discussed what what would you
say yeah well one thing that I'll say is
U I'm not evaluating many policies uh if
you think of a neural network as a
function
approximator uh you're like well what
function is it approximating so uh when
someone has a modelbased architecture uh
essentially they're giving you a
function they're saying I have two
functions I have the model function and
I have a planning function so the model
function uh is going to produ uh produce
roll out in some hypothetical
environment uh and uh that's a function
that's like modeling environment and
then a planning function is an algorithm
that says given a model function how do
I decide what to do next and so with
modelbased uh RL uh you've uh
partitioned the function into two
components uh and then you try to either
learn or engineer them separately so
typically in modelbased RL you try to
learn the model function but you keep
the inference function uh
algorithmically fixed uh uh in an
endtoend model fre AR you're like look
I'm not even going to bother separating
the two functions because uh if you
think about it uh uh keeping them
separate having them separate might give
you an easier learning problem it's
easier to learn a decomposed fun two
decomposed functions than a joint one
learning a composed function uh gives
you a lot more degrees of freedom so
it's harder to learn but it also means
that sometimes you do more planning
sometimes you do less planning sometimes
as you're planning you might decide oh
actually uh in this part of the planning
space I want to do a lot more I want to
focus a lot more on uh roll outs so um
I'm pretty agnostic to whether the right
architecture is modelbased versus model
free and my framework uh allows you to
play with both and that's a whole
research direction of like okay what is
the right agent architecture right now
it's a model-free uh single neural
network uh uh that's uh essentially
internally in ways that we don't
understand is doing whatever modeling
and planning that uh we want to do I
think it would be really cool to say hey
will we get better architectures if we
break it up into a modeler like a model
and a planner uh can we actually get
better performance but I think these are
all empirical questions uh I don't think
there's an a priori um you know better
architecture for it I want to play play
with both uh and I think either way what
you're try to learn is a bunch of
heuristics awesome great points and and
super interesting and so again it's the
flexibility of of active inference as
the topology of the compute goes from
the sparer more interpretable more kind
of single node semantic more definable
Etc on through the dense Universal
function approximator open-endedness
many many many architectures already
existing and many to come in that area
and then together they're approximating
an
approximator and then you have to
engineer it pragmatically either way so
then in practice these considerations
like are are empirical because they just
relate to how you build it and so um
it's on your GitHub like what repo
should people look at just to be like
clear with that answer what repos should
people look at what will happen when
they just get started with it
yeah um let me yeah show show it if you
can thank you
yeah um so can you see this uh yeah so
the re uh the repo is uh under GitHub
daveta um and there's U there links to
the Discord probably the best way to get
I mean uh so there is a an overview and
getting started
uh I'm in the middle of a big
environment rewrite so some of these
things are going to change soon uh and
if you're actually seriously thinking
about um working on this uh I'd urge you
to reach out to me uh and uh uh on
Discord or email me because I can help
you get started more quickly uh there's
also a research road map uh uh here
where um I just have like a bunch of
ideas of things that people can play
with that are of low hanging F uh
um but yeah the repo is uh on GitHub dve
meta that's epic thank you okay next
questions um Courtney has two questions
first
one regarding the question about how you
test whether or not has
introspection and that you would like
help with that research what skill set
are you looking for in collaborators
um I mean I can use collaborators with a
lot of different skill sets uh I mean
what I would really love is someone uh
like uh at like a co-founder
collaborator level someone that thinks
about this stuff day and night like I do
that would want to uh basically be like
a deep collaborator so like software
engineer uh ml experience so that's like
on the most uh intense like co-founder
level but then there's so much other
research to be done so uh uh I I shared
this like Behavior Uh Gallery here uh so
this uh you know here you know these
agents are trained under different
scenarios and then we take them out of
context and we're like okay what do they
do in an empty room what do they do in a
bigger empty room what happens if we uh
you know took take uh two agents
and stick them in a room with finite
resources like how do they behave doing
this kind of research is uh requires
almost no technical skills you basically
have to um uh think about like what kind
of uh environment do I want to design
and then you edit some configuration
files to be like okay let's make you
know five mty rooms put two agents in
there put some food run the simulation
and then measure this thing so uh that
can be someone with uh very low
technical uh capabilities but just like
someone that wants to think critically
about uh uh like Hey how do we study
this new life form uh or this new
intelligence um uh I can also use uh
people that are uh excited to be like
technical communicators and like write
and share these ideas and get them uh
into written form uh to be shared more
broadly I can use help with u uh people
that uh want to do like uh uh find
collaborators or do like Outreach to
other developers uh around uh getting
these environments used or getting
people to help with them so I think uh
just like um uh a broad set of skills uh
but uh the ones that are the easiest for
me to leverage are going to be uh
people with a coding and software
experience that want to actually help uh
build some of these components and that
can be just like uh that that that does
not need to be like AI experience just
software uh being uh excited to write
software is sufficient thank you great
answer what over this process has
surprised you the most slash what have
you learned in this journey so far
like about the model output or how it
related to some of the other engineering
just any aspect about
it yeah I mean one thing that uh and
this shouldn't be surprising but things
are hard things take way longer than you
think they're going to take and it's
usually the hard the hard stuff is not
some like complex uh algorithm it is
just like building stuff uh getting it
to work uh before I dove into the world
of reinforcement learning I had no idea
how uh nent that field is pretty much
everyone working on RL is like RL is
really hard it almost doesn't work uh
there uh it's just like it's a very
young field and uh so on the one hand uh
uh like that was surpris surprising it's
also really surprising how much of
mainstream RL is working on stuff that I
uh I have hard time getting excited
about like most of RL is trying to play
uh pong they're trying to uh you know be
like can we play Atari games better than
we played than these other algorithms
play Atari games and that's not fair to
the entire field but there's very little
research going into uh using uh
reinforcement learning in these complex
open-ended environments it's like almost
no one is working on that uh and RL uh
and then U yeah I guess th those are
some surprises for me this is just like
a Green
Pastures very interesting it it relates
to something I've heard many times in
the kind of ACM area is what are the
benchmarks so other than just the
computational resourcing and all those
kinds of performance like how how do you
think about benchmarking when arguably
that will have open-endedness in certain
ways or conditionalities or or
possibilities yeah great question uh and
I've given this a lot of thought and I I
don't have like a perfect answer but I
have a direction um so I would say two
things one uh I think uh uh what I
started with is behavior catalog but I
think one there's like a behaviorist
empirical study that you could do to
these agents so you could be like okay
we trained these agents in these
open-ended worlds now if we take them
out of their um context and actually try
to do cognitive tests on them how well
do they do you know can we uh offer it
poison berries uh in addition to normal
berries and will it learn to avoid them
uh can you uh uh how in the same way
that we try to quantify the intelligence
of animals it's like okay can you train
it can you talk to it can you convince
it how much training does it need can it
Sol like does it have memory like if you
set it up in a situation where it needs
to remember five things uh does it work
what about 10 things what about 50 um
and so a lot of this is uh up to the
researchers intelligence rather than the
entities's intelligence is like can we
be smart enough to figure out how to
test for cognitive ability so that's One
Direction and then the other direction
is pure comp uh competitive Fitness so
if you have two uh policies you you have
two different brains um and you have one
control 10 agents and the other one
control 10 agents which ones will get
more free energy so essentially like an
ELO style competitive uh uh evaluations
U of policies is the other direction and
that gets tricky because maybe uh you
know in a world where brain a controls
One agent and brain b controls uh uh 10
agents uh is going to have a different
outcome where brain a controls 10 agents
and brain one B controls One agent so
you uh there's still some uh settings
you got to test uh head-to-head
competition under a variety of different
settings and you can imagine that some
do better in resource Rich environments
where others do better in resource poor
environments so you have to be careful
around uh trying to quantify um uh
superiority but I think overall we
should get to a point where you can say
hey look under a lot of conditions this
new brand that we trained um is able to
outperform this old brain that we
trained u in a competitive setting and
then we have a bunch of evals that are
measuring things like memory
trainability uh ability to uh solve
problems and not get stuck at local
Optima and it's uh performing better on
this set of evals so I think it is a
quantifiable uh approach uh is just uh
it's not it's not
trivial yeah great answer how do they do
it in other systems okay here's a
question from board
guy do you make there's a few pieces of
clarification do you make a distinction
between concepts of peie wise versus
nonlinear learning in the context of
emergence more specifically do you think
of these types of measures as a lack of
knowledge about what the system is doing
on our end as in the nonlinearity is
simply the peace wise measure not tested
right do you think of these two measures
the the continu the continuous nonlinear
and the peie wise as representative as
two surely different learning rules or
are we simply testing the model in the
wrong
ways if I followed all of that but uh uh
and feel free to rephrase the question
if I'm not answering what you're asking
but um I uh the part that really
resonated for me uh is
uh uh and I I've moved really heavy in
this direction uh a lot of what we're
talking about is not I don't think there
is you know what is the system doing
what is its learning rule there is what
what are our beliefs about its learning
rules so a lot of what we're talking
about is as observers what do we uh how
do we model the system uh and we could
model it as having uh learning rule a
with like uh a lot lot of competence or
learning rule B with less competence or
a set of learning rules that are
interacting uh in nonlinear ways uh so
uh partially this is the way we uh we
would talk about the model rather than
what is the model doing itself and so I
think with that formulation I'm uh I'm
not that I guess interested in like what
is uh like what is the model actually
doing I'm more interested in like can
what can we measure about this model's
Behavior so uh what um when we look at
the behavior of an agent is it acting in
a way that we think is intelligent and
uh uh and maybe that's what you're
asking uh rather than you know what is
the neural network doing internally and
how much and uh uh it's interesting
because uh the Dynamics are highly
nonlinear what the network is doing is
reacting to what the other agents are
doing which is also what the network is
doing so it's essentially uh uh
conditioned on its own conditioning so
there I don't think there is any kind of
like tractable linear way to decouple
these behaviors it's highly recurrent
and highly
nonlinear that's a a great answer a few
other aspects is the the concept of
figure and ground kind of like
agent-based modeling in an environment
that is like a grid World environment
that is one topology and so there's kind
of that statistical dense click that is
the input output whether that's trained
end to end or in the two separate
sections and then there's that's like a
bumper car with either the niche read
and WR Andor the long uh scale
Communications like you brought in later
so then the then especially when you
bring in all these fluctuating knobs
like let's just say that we learn
certain behavioral policies when we're
in a bright room versus when we can't
see then environmental discontinuity
which is something that that
experimentor has done to again reflect
that relational piece it would
discontinuously change it but then it's
just like yes but the Neal networks
continuous value numbers Etc it's like
that's like a deflationary account
because we already know know what
structure our map approximator is it's
just the
statistics so it's it's like interesting
about is this like applying active
inference with reinforcement learning or
one or the other and then it's like but
you just look at the open source code
and there's like and then it could be
composed another way and having the
ability to swap out different kinds of
methods for each other helps highlight
like that flexibility
MH he wrote I guess the way you think
about these has implications about
whether you can simply scale it up if
you add more
variables
um I guess more variables uh there's uh
there's two places to add variables uh
one place is in the complexity of the
environment so as we add more uh uh
Behavior like more objects and more uh
diversity into the environment uh there
is essentially the environment becomes
more complex but really the main source
of variables is the number of parameters
in the models and I I assume that's what
you're mostly talking about and really
again from the agent perspective the
environment is all of the other all of
the other models on the other side of
you so for every agent you have a neural
network with say 10 million parameters
but your environment is 50 other agents
Each of which has 10 million parameters
and what you do uh and what you perceive
is going to depend on what those
networks are doing and so yeah the idea
is to scale this by uh training larger
and larger neural networks and uh the
larger the neural n the more parameters
your neural network has the more uh it's
capable uh the more complexity it's
capable of representing but the harder
it is for you to train it and the more
uh comput and uh you need so yeah the
whole point of this project is uh so in
RL uh uh typically the models we train
are a few hundred thousand to maybe uh a
few million parameters uh in language
models we're training you know 70
billion 100 billion uh parameter
networks uh and uh the idea is to try to
make infrastructure and an environment
that is so fast for generating training
data that we can uh train up these
really large High parameter neural
networks so that they can
generalize uh over dealing with really
complex environmental spaces and
essentially that so that they can learn
complex learning algorithms uh
themselves uh so yeah the whole point is
to add more and more variables to the
neural network great point and that
highlights that the
in the in the agent versus the niche
situation is averted because the
resourcing of the niche is so much
greater because it's only 10 versus
versus if there's 100 other agents or
something then it's only 1% of the
resources per agent that that even that
kind of structurally prepares a very
different environment than a dietic even
dietic
collaborative stationary training
Paradigm so there's a lot there with the
movement and also the very cool so um
any last comments otherwise I hope this
has been exciting for people to learn
more and to to look at the GitHub and
get
involved anything
else oh sorry are you asking me or are
you asking do you have anything else oh
um no thank you so much for your time uh
feel free to join the Discord uh here
I'll bring the link back up uh uh and
also uh feel free to message me if you
want to chat or collaborate in any way
um uh yeah I mean for me this has uh
been a really fun project and I'm just
like excited to keep working on it and
finding other people that want to work
on it with me epic okay thank you David
bye yeah thank you Daniel
bye e